The coral gravel that sleeps under the sea of sand,
沙海深處長眠的珊瑚
or the carpets with gold and silver interwoven,
金絲銀線交織的絨毯
or the rainbow-colored honey that can only be eaten by the people in heaven,
天上人食用的七彩蜂蜜
there is nothing I need among them.
這些我們都不需要
We only want what you have given us.
我們留在手中的 是你賦予我們的東西
We are the halves of the soul, that will never be apart.
我們是永世比翼連理的 靈魂的分身
With the purist tears in our eyes, let us wait for the moment when we can eventually see each other.
如今讓我們飽蘸著至純的淚水 等待能夠再度相見的時刻
July 20, 93 S.S.
砂刑曆93年 7月20日
We had a joint funeral at the beard square.
在鬍鬚廣場舉行聯合沙葬
Hakuji-sama and the people of mud whale are flowed to the sand.
為沙海所吞噬的 是哈庫奇爺爺和泥鯨的人民
As well as the enemy soldiers died in the battle with us.
此外 還有戰死的敵軍士兵
Bye bye!
掰掰
Sienna... Tell me why...
希艾娜…為什麼…
Why did you choose to suicide?
為什麼你會自己尋死…
Captain, see her face for the last time please.
團長 請最後再看她一眼
Her hair...
把她的頭髮…
Cut a piece of Sienna's hair, and leave it to me.
把她的頭髮剪一綹留下來
Why don't you see her off? She is your wife!
自己的妻子 為什麼竟不肯為她送行？
Who are you...
誰啊 你是…
Whose tear is it...
這眼淚是誰的
What's a pity, Shuan.
真可憐啊 朱安
We may save the apatheia without hearts, but no one can save you.
被掠去心靈的士兵都還有救
You are so cold, my mother.
真冷淡啊 「媽媽」
See your face...
瞧瞧你這張臉
at the sea yourself.
自己到水邊照看看吧
It's like the demon is laughing.
就好像惡靈的笑容一般
Demon... Yeah.
惡靈…啊
Huh...Hahaha...
哈哈哈
Hahaha!
哈哈哈！
Translator
翻
ssnake
譯
静寂よ　旋律よ　儚き印よ
ssnake
Silence and melody, and the transient lives of Shirushi
静寂よ　旋律よ　儚き印よ
Timing
時 間 軸
zwc1991
zwc1991
砂上にこの地に　生き続けたのなら
砂上にこの地に　生き続けたのなら
If you have been living on the land, on the sea of sand
如果是在這沙海之上  生活下去
罪を纏う世界から　鯨の歌を聴いた...
罪を纏う世界から　鯨の歌を聴いた…
In a sinned world, we have heard the whale's lied
在罪業重重的世界裡  我們曾側耳傾聽鯨魚的歌唱…
運命を　感情を　抱くべき子たちよ
運命を　感情を　抱くべき子たちよ
Our fate and our emotions, my beloved children
不論命運  還是感情  親愛的孩子們喲
さ  き
さ  き
その先へ　その未来へ
その先へ　その未来へ
Towards the future, go ahead
向著未來  向著前方
導かれたのなら
導かれたのなら
If you can be our guide
只要有你指引前路
幾千の声　空想の地へ
幾千の声　空想の地へ
Thousands of words, leaving for the fantasy lands
萬千寄語  向著空想的彼岸
舵を切って行こうとした
舵を切って行こうとした
Steering towards the opposite
相信信念調轉方向
バラード
バラード
幾千の声　砂の海の譚歌
幾千の声　砂の海の譚歌
Thousands of songs, they are the ballads of the sea of sand
萬千歡聲  是沙海的歌謠
F
雪 飄 工 作 室
L
雪 飄 工 作 室
After the attack from skulax,
斯奇洛斯的襲擊之後
We were trying to regain our everyday lives step by step.
大家慢慢開始恢復日常生活
Ne...
涅…
Hey!
喂！
Why are you here?
你來幹什麼
I made some galenicals.
我把做好的藥帶來了
It is the nutrient to extend the short lives of Shirushi,
本來是為了改善印的短命
that I have been researching on.
而研製的營養劑
Please let him drink it after he wake up.
等他醒來了 請餵他服用
It's your fault.
…都怪你
Cuz you have chosen Oni into the assault team,
都怪你把歐尼選入突擊隊
he got into...
才會變成這樣…
And Nibi...
還有尼比…
I am sorry.
對不起
I made you feel sad.
給你留下了悲傷的回憶
S... Stop it!
放…放開我！
Please let me promise.
我願意保證
I will never, make anybody fight anymore.
再也不會與人爭戰
Nobody will fight.
再也不會讓人參戰
Since now we have known Oni has the power to destroy a Nous,
雖然如今大家都知道了歐尼有著能夠破壞魂形的力量
somebody may persuade us on starting a war.
或許會有人說起要發動戰爭
But there will be victims for each battle.
但是只要有紛爭 就會有人犧牲
There will be people hurt.
就會有人受傷
Therefore I am thinking about a peaceful way.
…所以 我會考慮避免戰爭的方法
I will protect everyone next time.
下次由我來 保護大家
Kids, say thank you to Oni.
大家進來向歐尼致謝吧
Thank you, Oni.
謝謝你 歐尼
You helped the mud whale.
泥鯨得救了喔
The nutrient juice by Suo is bitter, but drink it.
蘇澳的營養汁很苦 但要喝哦
We will bring you more presents when you wake up.
等你醒來了我們還會帶好多禮物來的
Also thank you, Kicha!
也謝謝綺茶
Suo, the presbyters are calling you.
蘇澳 長老們在找你
The presbyters?
長老們？
Yeah.
是的
What?
嗯？
Lykos?
黎可斯？
After they withdrew from the mud whale,
從泥鯨撤退之後
how are the soldiers been?
士兵們去幹什麼了？
They should have returned to the mother ship.
他們大概已經回到母艦了
sentikinesis
thymia
However, the power of lifeboats is the thymia of soldiers.
只是 避難艇的動力源是士兵們的情念力
I wonder if they have enough stamina to get back to the mother ship...
不知道他們的體力還能不能撐到回到母艦
They may be exhausted...?
或許會精盡人亡？
Yeah...
是的…
Hey! Stop it!
哇 快停下
Shhh!
噓～！
Won't the mother ship attack us?
那個母艦不會襲擊過來吧？
I believe they won't in the meanwhile.
我覺得短時間內不會
How do you know?
為什麼你這麼判斷？
νοῦς
νοῦς
Because Nous is an indispensable defense to prevent the invasion from other countries.
為了防禦他國入侵 魂形是必不可缺的
σκύλος
σκύλος
The lost of Skulax the Nous for the empire,
對帝國來說 這次失去魂形·斯奇洛斯
will become an significant blunder of my brother,
是作為法萊那殲滅作戰的提案者及指揮官的我哥哥的重大失敗
ἐκκλησία
ἐκκλησία
Without the approval of the Emperor and the supreme chairman of the Soul Church,
無法想像他能在沒有獲得皇帝陛下和魂召會最高議長的承認的情況下
νοῦς
νοῦς
it is impossible to dispatch a ship with a Nous.
驅使載有魂形的船舶
So it is sure to say we are safe for the time being, right?
也就是說暫時可以安心了吧
Perhaps.
大概是
But it is just my prediction, and I am just a soldier.
但是 這不過是一介小兵的我個人的預測
I can hardly believe my brother will obey the punishment.
我不覺得哥哥會就這樣老老實實的接受處分
Masuo, have you got up?
瑪索 你醒了嗎？
Yo, old guy.
喔 大叔啊
What the hell you are here, I just get slept.
搞什麼啊 好不容易能睡個覺
It's omasa bamboo alcohol.
給你 大真沙竹酒
Alcohol?
酒？
But I'm just a shirushi. Can I drink it?
我們印能喝嗎
I thought it is banned because we may lose our controls of thymia.
不是因為說擔心情念力失控而禁止的嗎？
Ah, it means you are no longer worrying about that...
啊 是已經不用擔心我了嗎…
It is prepared by Shinono.
希諾諾專門給你的
By her...
…這樣啊
Then, I'll drink it without hesitation.
那我不客氣了
See you.
再見
Oh, wait!
啊 等等
Have a drink with me.
你也陪我喝一杯
Ah... No!
啊…不要！
ολιβίνης
這可是奧莉薇尼斯給我的重要的東西
Oh...
哇
What?
哇！
It's an animal?
原來是生物嗎！
It's food?
原來是食物嗎！
Ah!
啊！
We can no longer eat it if it runs away!
讓它逃了就吃不到了！
We can't eat it!
可不能吃它！
What's that?
這是什麼東西！
Hey! Don't run away!
喂 別逃！
Chakuro!
查克羅
You guys have eavesdropped?
你們偷聽了嗎？
κόκαλο
κόκαλο
Hey, Kókkalo!
喂 骨頭！
Kókkalo? Is that Kókkalo?
骨頭？ 那個是？
We are sincerely sorry!
對不起！
Hey!
喂！
Hey, how can you drink that fast.
喂 你這一口氣就喝光了可不好
Don't be angry...
別生氣嘛
Why are you being so cold...
為什麼你這麼冷漠啊
Kucchi...
庫奇！
Who's Kucchi!
誰是庫奇啊！
I'm worrying about you, Kucchi!
我可擔心庫奇了啦
You must be lonely if I died!
要是我死了 你會寂寞的
I don't need your worry, you muscle brain.
我可沒道理讓你這樣的肌肉笨蛋擔心！
That's it!
是呢！
Well, after all,
不過 到頭來
we have to accept what's going to happen.
該怎麼樣就會怎麼樣的
Well, what's wrong with you...
真是的… 你到底是怎麼回事啊…
After all the sadness, the people of mud whale still
在度過慘痛的難關之後 泥鯨上的人們
believed that they could get back to their everyday lives.
依然對能夠回到往昔的日常堅信不疑
No, they were hoping that.
不 是衷心祈願
Oh, our master is finally back home.
哎呀 主人你可總算回來了
What's up? Don't be hesitate.
怎麼了 不用客氣
They are my precious pierrots.
大家都是我寶貴的小丑
Oh my god, he is bringing a girl home.
哎呀 真討厭 這個人帶女人回來了
He worth our esteem.
士別三日當刮目相待呢
Even me, was a playboy in the past.
老夫當年也是以此馳名的呢
You liar!
別說瞎話！
What?
什麼？
It's not a lie! The only thing I have changed...
可不是騙你的 發生變化的…
is my head!
只有我的腦袋啊
What's up?
怎麼了？
ἐκκλησία
ἐκκλησία
The inquest by the Soul Church will soon be undertaken.
你不是馬上就要接受魂召會的審問了嗎
It is not the time for laughing...
這可不是談笑風生的場合…
It's fine.
沒問題
I have already had the strategy in my head.
我心裡有數
In your head?
心裡？
This guy is planing to do that again.
又打算下手了 這個人
His story is the greatest in the world.
誇誇其談可是天下一絕
Shut up!
吵死了！
Your laughs as well as the voices of your castrated pierrots
你這傢伙的笑聲和這幫小丑太監一樣的聲音
are provoking me!
最讓人惱火了！
It seems he is in a mood because he failed to make friends with us.
看來被排斥在外讓你心情不太好呢
Ah...
啊…
Is it... a dog?
狗…嗎？
It's not dog.
不是狗
It's a lion.
是「獅子」
You are the guy on Skulax...
你是斯奇洛斯上的…
I added you into the list of death by error.
我…不小心把你寫到戰死名單裡去了
Don't mind.
沒關係
It's better treat him as dead.
當他死了還好些
φάλαινα
φάλαινα
When is... the next attack to Fallaina?
法萊那… 下次襲擊定在什麼時候了？
I have to go Fallaina!
我必須要去法萊那！
There is nothing else that can make me happy!
再也沒有 別的開心事了
There is only one way.
只有一個方法
Become my pierrot.
來當我的小丑
λιοντάρι
λιοντάρι
Ryotari.
柳達理
What?
哎？
You must be kidding...
這怎麼可能…
How can I... become a fucking pierrot...
我怎麼會去…當什麼小丑…
I can bring you to the war if you are my personal belonging.
成為我的東西的話 就能一起上戰場
It's the only way.
你已經只剩這個方法了
No... No way...
不…不要
I hate that!
我不要 這種事情…
How can I become a fucking pierrot!
我怎麼能當小丑這種鬼東西
It's bad to say fucking pierrot!
怎麼能說咱們是這種鬼東西呢
Be easy, it's fun.
沒關係的 很好玩的
You should fit it.
你啊一定很擅長的
Isn't this good? It just fit you!
比如這個怎麼樣 挺適合你的
In the mud whale, we depends on the rains to get water supply.
泥鯨上的生活用水依賴於雨水
It was said that the river of the heaven
傳說在池子裡玩水
will flow down if we play water in the pond.
會讓天上的大河滿溢 灑落人間
So we went playing water if it did not rain for a while.
因此如果一段時間沒有降雨 大家就會去玩水
What a waste!
太浪費了！
What?
什麼？
What are you doing, Ginshu?
你幹什麼啊銀淑
Don't cry!
眼淚啊
We are lacking of water, bear it!
咱們正缺水呢 忍著！
It hurts!
好痛啊
After all, the tears will be accumulated in the pond, why can't I cry?
反正淚水也會貯在池子裡的啊 沒關係不是
Ah, you're right.
啊 這樣啊
What are you doing there?
你在幹什麼啊
I'm crying to increase the water here!
哭出來增加池水啊！
Hey, you should also cry!
喂 你們幾個也給我哭！
People can smile again, soon after the sorrow.
悲痛之後 人仍然能夠歡笑
Why do people have such an unstable and uncertain
為什麼人會有著
feeling called emotion?
這樣不穩定而不確定的感情？
Suo-sama, don't your fingers hurt?
蘇澳哥哥你手手不痛嗎？
You are clenching your fingers too much!
不能這麼拚命扣緊雙手的！
Hey, if you are not acting happily, there won't be rains!
是啊 不玩得開心的話是不會下雨的
...You are right.
…是的呢
What?
嗯？
Don't say enemies are coming again!
難不成敵人又來了？
No, that's not the ship of the empire.
不 那不是帝國的船
So it's from another country?
難道是別的國家？
...The crest of blue hourglass?
…藍色沙漏的紋章？
If they can be our friends,
要是能拉進我們這邊的話
it is possible to help everyone without war.
就能避免戰爭 拯救大家
What the hell the milk smelling!
怎麼一股乳臭！
There is indeed a sweet smell like milk.
確實有一股奶香一樣的甜味呢
But be careful, Roharito-sama.
但是 羅哈里特大人 請萬分小心
It is an unknown island that we have never seen in our country.
這是我國此前從未遇到的
No!
哇
It hurts...
啊好痛
Welcome to the mud whale.
歡迎來到泥鯨
My name is Suo. I am the chief here.
我是這裡的首長 蘇澳
Did you get across the sea of sand and come here?
你們是穿越沙海來到這裡的嗎？
Are you OK, Foni?
沒事吧 佛尼
Are you OK?
你沒事吧
May I help you?
有什麼我能幫助你的…
Wha..wha..what a beautiful nudist!
美美美 美形的裸族！
How can the sturdy female warriors Gígantas be like this!
堅強的女戰士 季甘達姐妹怎麼能是這副醜態
I am the son of the Duke of Amonlogia of the United Kingdom of Sidelasia.
寡人乃蘇益德拉西亞聯合王國阿蒙洛基亞公領領主之子
Roharito Anastenagmós Neje-Immiskin Emarica Antipater Nor Amonlogia.
羅哈里特·阿納斯特納格莫斯·內埃-伊米斯金·艾瑪利卡·安特帕特羅斯·諾·阿蒙洛基亞
is my name!
以·上！
Too long!
真長！
Dear Roharito Anastenagmós Neje-Immiskin Emarica Antipater Nor Amonlogia.
羅哈里特·阿納斯特納格莫斯·內埃-伊米斯金·艾瑪利卡·安特帕特羅斯·諾·阿蒙洛基亞先生
Glad to see you!
非常高興認識您
He remembered!
記住了！
There can't be any rudeness even as little as a single sand grain during the first meet!
初次接觸
I think you said you're the chief here.
你說自己是首長？
Yes!
是的！
Then prepare the welcome party for us as soon as possible,
那麼 立刻準備招待寡人
the chief of nudists.
裸族之長
Nu...dists?
裸族？
Wha wha wha what have I done!
怎怎怎怎麼辦
It is as rude as a tank of sand!
這可比一大桶沙子還要失禮了…
Don't be ashamed, the chief of nudists!
沒什麼好害羞的 裸族之長！
I don't care about the differences in culture.
寡人不在意文化的差異
Huh?
哎？
I will accept you as you are!
我願接受袒露自我的你們！
Nezu, what's happening?
涅茲 怎麼樣了？
I will do my best to help you make your lives modern and cultural.
為了你們能夠過上先進的文化的生活
Immediately finish the procedure for make this island under my administration.
立刻開始進行讓這個島加入寡人統治範圍的手續
And claim the handover of all your rights to me.
命令你交出全部權力
What are you talking about?
你在說什麼啊
Didn't you just say,
你不是剛剛才說過
you will accept us as an equal?
願意以同等的地位接受我們嗎
Suocchi!
蘇澳澳！
You can't, Ginshu!
不可以 銀淑！
You will make it a war again!
又會釀成戰爭的！
How can I be equal with you?
寡人哪裡跟你們「同等」了？
You are the monkeys that can do nothing!
你們這群什麼都不會的猴子
I will show you ignorant guys the power of Restraingun with our country's prides.
就讓無知的你們
Well...
哎呀呀
Captain!
團長！
With such a small number of people who seems to be unable to use thymia,
thymia
how can you be as conceit as that.
居然還敢這麼囂張
We should just seize them.
看來立刻抓起來才是解決之道呢
Roharito-sama,
羅哈里特大人
it is impossible to deal with that number.
這個數量我們不是對手
Please surrender to them.
請提起投降
Ganva, what did you say?
岡瓦啊 你說什麼？
Why do I have to surrender to them!
為何寡人必須要投降
Because you are the master of us.
因為你是大家的主人
Ehh...
唔…
Are you hungry?
你餓了嗎？
How poor you are.
好可憐
Let me prepare your meals right away!
我們立刻為你準備餐食
Tasteless!!!
難吃！
Tasteless tasteless tasteless tasteless tasteless tasteless!
難吃難吃難吃難吃難吃難吃！
It is as rich as the best milk and has a fruity fragrance...
高檔牛奶一般的醇厚而又帶著水果的芳香…
It is the first time I have eaten such a tasteless food~~~!
我還是第一次吃到這麼難吃的東西！
Call the head chef here!
給我把廚師長叫來！
Huh? You mean the children who boiled this?
哎 但這是小孩子們煮的
What? You just boiled it?
什麼 只是煮過而已嗎
There are so many bamboos you can pick in the groves in the center of this island.
島中央的竹林裡能採到許多
I see.
原來如此
The bamboo shoots are the reason why this island smells like milk.
這個島的乳臭味是因為這個竹筍嗎
I want it!
想要！
I will take this back to Amonlogia!
寡人要把這個帶回阿蒙洛基亞去！
But the freshness is the most important for bamboo shoots...
但是 竹筍最要緊的是新鮮…
Of course,
當然是
I will take back the whole groves!
把竹林帶回去
And the whole island!
連這個島一起
What?
什麼？
What is that fucking guy talking about?
在說什麼呢 這傢伙
Excuse me.
不對
What are you talking about, my dear guest?
您有什麼要求嗎 尊敬的客人
Be quick! Let's move this island!
去 快點開動這個島
Make it heads to Amonlogia!
向阿蒙洛基亞開去
What the hell are you talking about?
你這傢伙在說什麼呢
Excuse me.
不對
What the fucking stupid things have you just said, my dear guest?
您怎麼能提出這麼愚蠢的要求呢 尊敬的客人
Our mud whale has been wandering without control for decades.
我們泥鯨這幾十年來
Nobody knows where we are going.
誰都不知道會去向何方
Move it? Head to somewhere?
開動它？向著哪？
If we could make it, we weren't suffering that much!
要能做到這種事就不會這麼辛苦了！
Lykos?
黎可斯？
I wanna be alone for a while.
我想一個人待一會…
Lykos... She is strange since the guests came.
黎可斯 從客人來了以後神情一直怪怪的
I wonder if she became homesick.
難不成是想回去了什麼的？
No no no!
不會不會不會的！
κόκαλο
κόκαλο
Kókkalo!
骨頭！
Emma!
艾瑪！
Great! I've been looking for you.
太好了！ 我一直在找你
I wanna ask you about this puppy.
我想就這個小東西問問你
I got it from a girl named Olivines I met on Skulax.
它是在斯奇洛斯上見到的一個叫奧莉薇尼斯的女孩子給我的
So you are the one who got it?
這是你拿到的？
Ah... Yeah...
啊…嗯
You are really great...
果然你最棒了
...I didn't mean I'll give it to you.
不是要給你
I wanna ask you what it is.
是想問問你它是什麼東西
You have told me that
你不是說過戰爭結束了
after the war you will tell me the secret of Fallaina, right?
就把法萊那的祕密告訴我的嗎
Fine. As a reward...
行啊 作為獎勵
κόκαλο
κόκαλο
φάλαινα
φάλαινα
Fallaina will go on a new journey after getting the bone.
得到骨頭的法萊那 將踏上新的旅途
What this puppy is, and the story of Fallaina and sinners,
這個小東西是什麼 還有法萊那和罪人的故事
I will show you all of them...
全都給你看
κόκαλο
κόκαλο
Kókkalo!
骨頭？
Wings...
翅膀…
Emma... What's going on... What's it?
艾瑪…怎麼回事啊…這是？
The mud whale is steered?
泥鯨能轉舵了？
Didn't you think it's strange?
你沒覺得奇怪嗎？
Both Lykos' ship and the battleship Skulax
黎可斯的船和戰艦斯奇洛斯
νοῦς
νοῦς
can moving towards a destination if they have nous on board.
搭載有魂形的船都能控制方向行進
φάλαινα
φάλαινα
But Fallaina wasn't able.
但是 法萊那卻不行
Because Fallaina was a prison of exile, one part of it has been deprived.
法萊那是流放的監獄 因此被剝奪了
The rudder...
「舵」
κόκαλο
κόκαλο
νοῦς
νοῦς
The bone is exactly the rudder for ships with nous.
骨頭 是魂形的船的「舵」啊
Steer yourselves from now on.
接下來就由大家來掌舵了
Cuz life is a fight.
生命就是戰場
Living, seizing, and burning yourselves.
生存 掠奪 燃燒自我
In that night, we people on the mud whale had a dream.
這天晚上 泥鯨的人們做了一個夢
A little girl came to our beds and got into our ears.
小小的少女來到床邊 進到耳朵裡面
The girl sang a magical song in our heads.
少女在腦海裡唱起不可思議的歌謠
And acted as if she was praying.
做出祈禱的樣子
That was so sad that we all cried, and waked up.
不知為何 那是如此悲傷 讓人落淚而醒
And the girl came out as a drop of tear,
但少女化作淚水流落出來
faded away from the windows...
消失在了窗外
The tenth section
第 十 節
Go on a new journey
第 十 節
乾いた海の跡　望んで
乾いた海の跡　望んで
Staring into the trace of the dried sea
眺望昔日的大海
I will draw the other side I have never seen
まだ見ぬ対岸を描く
まだ見ぬ対岸を描く
描繪未知的彼岸
囚われの心のままなら
囚われの心のままなら
If you remain your heart in captivity
如果囚禁起心靈  一如過往
You may live without knowing the pain
こんな傷みも知らずにいた
こんな傷みも知らずにいた
又怎麼會經歷如此悲傷
The one who told the beautiful story
美しい詞を告げたひと
美しい詞を告げたひと
是誰講述起美好的希望
Can not wait for the dawn
夜明けも待たずに
夜明けも待たずに
讓我等不及黎明
Until beyond the end of world, I am swimming
果てのその先を泳ぐ
果てのその先を泳ぐ
向著天涯海角揚帆起航
Listen to the insects' song
虫の唄
虫の唄
徹夜蟲鳴
That night is our memory
眠らず君と聞いた記憶
眠らず君と聞いた記憶
回憶裡與你一起側耳傾聽
Just link hand in hand
手を　ただ結んで
手を　ただ結んで
只是雙手相牽
No matter it is twilight or a distant country
半色でも　遠い国でも
半色でも　遠い国でも
不論夕陽  還是遠方
短い一章に生まれた夢を
短い一章に生まれた夢を
Born in a short chapter
在這短暫蒼渺的一章裡
But let us go and embrace that dream
抱きしめに行こう
抱きしめに行こう
一起追逐夢想
The eleventh section
第 十 一 節
Something about the dream
夢 話